Guide to the Brooke Astor Papers 1884-2007 MS 3157
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. General Correspondence, 1953-2002, 2007; .75 Linear feet
  - W. General, 1959-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 42)
    Correspondents include, among others, Earl of Warwick, Benjamin Welles, Kimba Wood, Shelby White, Jayne Wrightsman, James Watt, Phyllis C. Wagner, Jane Weinberger, Duke of Wellington, Paul Wright, Jerauld Wright, Torsten N. Wiesel, and Rev. James G. Wilders.
  - Walters, Barbara, 1980-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 43)
  - Z. General, 1983-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 44)
    Correspondents include, among others, Paul Zahl and Qais Abdul Munim al Zawawi.
  - Zilkha, Cecile, 1984 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 45)
  - Unidentified correspondents, 1976-1998 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 46)
  - Condolence letters re: Brooke Astor, 2007 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 47)
    Letters of condolence to Brooke Astor's son, Anthony Marshall, from New York Governor Andrew M. Cuomo, former New York mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, and travel writer Leila Hadley Luce.
- Series III. Writings by and about Brooke Astor, 1915-2005; 1 Linear feet
  The series primarily includes writings by Brooke Astor, ranging from typescripts of short essays, poetry and fiction, which may or may not have been published, to works in their published form, such as her autobiography "Footprints." The series also holds some of Astor's personal writings including diaries of 1915-17, a record of dinner parties for 1937-41, and journal entries for travel in 1962 (a cruise along the Italian coast) and 1995 (brief entries for a trip in Europe). Transcripts of some of Astor's public remarks and interviews of her are in the series. The series closes with some articles and other printed/published works about Brooke Astor. The container list provides more details about the content.
  The series is arranged with writings by Brooke Astor followed by interview transcripts and articles written about her. The writings by Astor are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Diaries, 1915-1917(?) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 48)
    3 typescripts of diary entries. One typescript of 13 pages dates from 1915 and a second typescript of 36 pages dates from 1917 (though one of the 1917 references is altered to read 1918 casting some doubt as to the actual year). The 1915 entries seems to refer to events in or around Washington, D.C. and the 1917/18 entries to Santiago. The entries center on personal and social concerns. The third diary entry dates from 1916, but is a typescript version from 2000. The entry centers on Brooke Russell kissing a boy and her thoughts about that, at the time and with a 2000 introductory comment about the difference in "falling in love" between 1916 and 2000.
  - Fiction writings?, 1930s? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 49)
    2 pieces that seem to be works of fiction, titled "Crepescule" and "An Emotional Experience." Authorship noted as Brooke Marshall.
  - Drawings by Brooke Russell, 1930s? (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    Two sheets of drawings: "Seen on the stage," a series of drawings of performers, initialed R.B.R, noted on back as Chap. 6; "Types of Greenwich Village," a series of captioned portraits, none initialed, noted on back as Ch. 11 or 12.
  - "Scratch a Russian", circa 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 50)
    Authored by Brooke Marshall, the piece can be dated by its opening which refers to Germany and Russia as allies. The piece, though, primarily tells a story in the first person dating from Peking (Beijing) in 1913-14; the context indicates that person cannot be Brooke and so may be fictional.
  - "The Joy of Living", 1930s? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 51)
  - Food-related, 1930s-1940s? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 52)
    2 versions of an essay on buffet suppers, one titled "Design for Dining" and another "Food for Thought" with recipes.
  - "Dinner party record", 1937-1941 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 53)
    Gift to Brooke from "Bud" (Charles Marshall) at Christmas 1936. Volume for recording dinner events, with plan of table, guests, menu, etc. Most pages have entries. Two loose sheets with seafood recipes are at the front of the volume.
  - "Values", 1960s? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 54)
  - Poetry and anecdote, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 55)
    Several short poems, one handwritten. Two printed poems are noted as having been written at ages 14 and 15. Also one fictional anecdote titled "A Bridge Game," with a mix of bridge references and African-American vernacular.
  - Reminiscences, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 56)
    3 pieces of personal memories (1 delivered as public remarks), one brief paragraph about Ronald Reagan, and one piece about Winterthur and Harry Dupont.
  - "D.S. Marandis" (original journal), 1962 July (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    Handwritten journal of travel from Venice, along Italian coast, ending at Monte Carlo, on board chartered ship Marandis. Inscribed by the ship's commanding officer. Guest signatures at front of volume, including Prince and Princess of Monaco.
  - "D.S. Marandis" (typescript), 1962 July (Offsite-box 2, Folder 57)
    Typescript of the original travel journal.
  - "The Cult of Ugliness", 1967 November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 58)
    Original title "Who killed beauty, and why?"
  - Speeches, 1973, 1976 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 59)
    Program, remarks introducing Astor, and Astor's remarks on the occasion of her receiving the Lotus Club's Medal of Merit (1973). 4th draft of a speech for the China Institute.
  - Toasts to/from Vartan Gregorian, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 60)
    Astor's toast to Gregorian on his second anniversary at New York Public Library, with an ode by Gregorian in response, signed by him. Also, a short paragraph, possibly for a public remark, about the founding of the library by John Jacob Astor.
  - Dogs, 1980s-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 61)
    Drafts of an article about Brooke Astor's 1930s dog, Fafner, with the final form as published in Home & Garden (1991). Also short pieces on the Kissinger's dog (Tyler), Bill Blass's dogs (Kate and Bruce), Barbara Walters's dog (Sale Goose), and Annette Reed's dog (Pickle).
  - Remarks at the Seraphic Society Luncheon, 1986 May 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 62)
  - Writings, 1987 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 63)
    3 pieces: An introduction for Thames and Hudson's publication of illustrations from "Bon Ton"; "The Re-Cycled Reader" for Home & Garden; and a paragraph "What a tree means to me" for Fairchild Publication's "W."
  - Writings on etiquette, 1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 64)
    A set of writings that seem to be intended for a small work on etiquette. Topics are: "Behavior at a dinner," "How men have changed," "Trustees," "Introducing people," Walking on a street," and "Don't get beyond yourself."
  - Writings, 1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 65)
    4 pieces: Statement in her capacity as president of the Vincent Astor Foundation in support of the landmark designation of City and Suburban York Avenue Estates; a comment on the New York Public Library's treasures for the New York Times Book Review; comments on "strapless formals" and comments on the seasons, likely for Home & Garden.
  - Writings, 1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 66)
    3 pieces: "Weddings"; "Dr. Livingston, I presume" [concerning marital infidelity]; and "Why I love New York."
  - Writings, 1991 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    2 pieces: An untitled item on the theme of personal discipline; and memories of the St. Regis Hotel, formerly owned by Vincent Astor.
  - Writings, 1994 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    2 pieces: "Sex" or "Hello Sex, What are you doing today?" and "Benefits" or "Benefits: Do let's not spread them too far."
  - Reminiscences, 1995, 1996, 1998 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    3 pieces: a reminiscence of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis for the catalogue of the exhibition "A tribute to Jackie"; a paragraph on Peggy Rockefeller for a book being prepared by the family; and a poem celebrating the 60th wedding anniversary of Anne and Brendan Gill.
  - Writings, 1995, 1999, 2000 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    3 pieces: an untitled dialogue between two friends discussing the prior night's dinner party they attended; "Refined flirting"; and "Death or divorce."
  - Diary, 1995 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes just a few days from September to October. Starts in Baden-Baden and concludes in New York. Just a few of the pages have entries.
  - "Footprints", 1980 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Brooke Astor's published autobiography.
  - "Questions and Some Answers", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    Slip-cased, printed volume of poetry by Brooke Astor.
  - Published articles authored by Brooke Astor, 1927, 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Holds one "letter about books" printed in Vogue in 1927, plus several articles by Brooke Astor published in magazines in the 1980s-90s.
  - Transcript of "Mrs. Vincent Astor in conversation with The Reverend Jesse Jackson", 1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Transcript of interview with Brooke Russell Astor '19", 1997, 2005 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Interview conducted by Dr. Elisabeth Griffith in connection with the oral history program of the Kathleen Galvin Johnson '53 Archives, The Madeira School. Interview held on November 7, 1997. Folder also holds a letter from 2005 to Anthony Marshall inquiring about the possibility of Brooke attending the school's Centennial Parade.
  - "They rolled out the red carpet: Brooke Astor interviewed by Roxana Robinson", 2000 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    Interview published in the Lincoln Center Theater Review, Fall 2000, number 26.
  - "Brooke Astor, Laureate of the Library", circa 1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    Typescript of remarks by Barbaralee Diamonstein.
  - "A birthday for Brooke", 1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    3 copies (of 4000) of a booklet printed under the auspices of the Citizens Committee for New York City on the occasion of Brooke Astor's 90th birthday. Includes a biographical sketch by Brendan Gill and several photographs from across her lifetime.
  - Magazine and other printed articles about Brooke Astor, 1966-1990s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    In addtion to articles, holds a list of articles published about Brooke Astor from 1982 to 1993.
  - New York Times Magazine article (2 copies)., 1991 November 17 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Photographs, circa 1885-2007; 3.75 Linear feet
  The series holds 8 photograph albums and a variety of loose photographs. The albums are listed individually in the container list. The earliest dates from about 1912 to 1916 and includes photographs of Brooke and others in China and Honolulu when Brooke's father was stationed there. Most of the albums date from the 1970s-1990s, with photographs of various social settings, receptions, dinners, and other events.
  The loose photographs range from the 1880s, depicting Brooke's grandparents, to the last years of Brooke's life in the 2000s. Some of these include her husbands Charles Marshall and Vincent Astor. Most are of social gatherings, receptions, events at New York Library and other institutions supported by Astor, and similar photographs.
  The series is arranged with albums first, followed by general photographs arranged roughly by format, subject and chronologically. Most of the photographs were boxed loose with no arrangement when delivered to N-YHS. The sorting of these photographs into the various folders noted in the container list was done by the processing archivist and is not a reflection of any original order.
  - Photograph album [1]., circa 1912-1916 (Offsite-box 5)
    Album of photographs, primarily snapshots from China. Brooke (Russell) Astor and her parents appear in several. Some are captioned. At the back are some color transparencies of artworks/drawings, likely by Brooke.
  - Photograph album [2]. "Mrs. Vincent Astor Jewels", 1927 (Offsite-box 5)
    A label in the album indicates it was compiled in 1927 so it is unclear which Mrs. Vincent Astor is being referred to.
  - Photograph album [3]. "Dedication of the bench in memory of Alexander Russell, Princeton University", 1977 July 28 (Offsite-box 5)
    Photos by Cliff Moore. Includes photos of those gathered for the dedication, with a typescript of the benediction by Rev. Richard N. Chrisman.
  - Photograph album [4]. Chinese Garden Court, Helmet Exchange, 1980 January 10 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Photographs removed from an album. Photos are of the hard hat exchange and press conference at the construction site of the Astor Chinese Garden Court in the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Photograph album [5]. Presidential Citizen's Award, 1988 (Offsite-box 4)
    Photographs from the presentation of the award to Brooke Astor by Ronald Reagan and from the following reception, at the White House.
  - Photograph album [6], circa 1989-1992 (Offsite-box 4)
    The contents are generally uncaptioned and undated, but dated items range from 1989-1992. Photos are primarily of Brooke Astor at various events, receptions, and social settings. Notable other people in the photos are Ronald Reagan, Nancy Reagan, Vartan Gregorian, Bob Hope, Barbara Bush, Edward Koch, and Norman Schwarzkopf, among many other unidentified individuals. There are photos from an Outward Bound outing; at the Metropolitan Museum of Art; with Marie Christopher when she was given the Brooke Russell Astor Award (1990); at the Seamen's Church Institute (groundbreaking/construction?); at the Arthur Ross birthday celebration (1991); a dog party; Morgan Library Christmas Party; etc. There is a thank you letter from Gregorian for Astor's endowment of the Bryant Park bookstack.
  - Photograph album [7], circa 1992-1995 (Offsite-box 4)
    The contents are generally uncaptioned and undated, but dated items range from 1993-1994. Photos are primarily of Brooke Astor at various events, receptions, and social settings. Notable other people in the photos are Ronald Reagan, Nancy Reagan, Vartan Gregorian, Mario Cuomo, Edward Koch, and Norman Schwarzkopf, among many other unidentified individuals. There are photos from the opening of the Bartow-Pell Carriage House (1993); at the Briarcliff Rotary Club; from various travels (Maine, Santo Domingo); and at the Hadrian Award Luncheon honoring David Rockefeller (1994); among others. Includes some letters of thanks and transmittals of photographs.
  - Photograph album [8], circa 1970, 1995-1997 (Offsite-box 4)
    The contents are generally uncaptioned and undated, but the bulk of the dated items range from 1994-1997. There are a small number of photos here that date from perhaps the 1970s. Photos are primarily of Brooke Astor at various events, receptions, and social settings. Notable other people in the photos are David Rockefeller and Felix Rohatyn, among many other unidentified individuals. There are photos from the Hadrian Award Luncheon honoring Lord Rothschild (1995) and The Aga Khan (1996), at the New York Public Library, with dogs and in gardens, among others. Includes some letters of thanks and transmittals of photographs.
  - Early photographs (4 folders), circa 1885-1930s? (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-5)
    Photos of Brooke Astor as a child through early adulthood, her parents and grandparents, and others, mostly unidentified. There are many copy prints of photos from Haiti and from China (many from photo album [1]). There may be some photos of Charles Marshall here as well.
  - Photographs. Charles Marshall, 1930s-1950s? (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    A small number of photos with Marshall. There may be others in the folders of early photographs.
  - Photographs. Vincent Astor (2 folders), 1940s?-1950s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7-8)
    One framed photo of Vincent with a dog; a carte-de-visite labeled as Vincent's father (as a child); slides of Ferncliff; portrait of Vincent in military uniform; Brooke and Vincent; and a photo-illustration of a pavilion for "Captain & Mrs. Vincent Astor" (1948).
  - Portrait photographs of Brooke Marshall/Brooke Astor, 1940s-2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs. New York Zoological Society (Bronx Zoo), circa 1980s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    Photos of elephants, including baby "Astor," gorillas, lions; Brooke Astor riding an elephant in the Asian section; and a group shot (of trustees?).
  - Photographs. Various black and white, circa 1964-1990s? (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    Dinners, social settings, celebratory events.
  - Photographs. Various color (2 folders), 1960s-2000s? (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18-19)
    Social settings, New York Public Library, interiors and exteriors of residences, dogs.
  - Photographs. Ambassador James Clement Dunn presenting credentials in Madrid, 1953 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs. Astor Court luncheon, 1991 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
    Luncheon hosted by Brooke Astor for the Asian Art Department of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Photographs of drawings of Brooke Astor, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - Postcard. Brooke Astor with Lillian Gish at Merchant's House Museum, 1982 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs. New York Public Library, 1990s? (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
  - Transparencies of artworks (by Brooke Astor?), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
    See also the back of photo album [1] for additional transparencies.
  - Oversize photographs (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
    Holds: Copy print of a 1914 photograph of Mrs. John Astor (Vincent's mother) in Statue of Liberty costume at the Anglo-American Peace Centenary pageant at Albert Hall (contextual note with photo); Brooke Astor with Lyndon Baines Johnson and Lady Bird Johnson; "library at 120 East End Ave; Vincent Astor's favorite red leather chair" (1959); 3 photos on-board Vincent Astor's yacht Nourmahal (circa 1928?); photo of a painting by Betsy Flagg Melcher of Brooke Astor (1963); Vincent Astor by building models (1950s?).
- Series V. Memorabilia, 1956-2007, undated; 1.75 Linear feet
  The series includes artifacts and other objects, mostly of a commemorative nature, related to the Astors or received by them. The container list provides an item level inventory.
  The series is presented in rough chronological order.
  - Match book covers, personalized with initials "VA" (Vincent Astor), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
    5 covers. Matches have been removed.
  - "Friends and Fellow Citizens: Washington's Address to the People of the United States, 1796", 1956 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
    Reproduction published by the New York Public Library for members of the Citizens Advisory Committee. This copy presented to Vincent Astor, whose name is embossed on the cover. Contextual correspondence with book.
  - Gag diploma, 1957 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
    Diploma awarded by Biltmore Hotel in Phoenix, Arizona, to Brooke for graduating class in "Latin Dances," etc.
  - Vatican City 1st Day Issue Stamps. "Sede Vacante MCMLVIII", 1958 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
  - "The Tall Ships Commemorative Postcard Collection; Cancelled in Moscow, July 4, 1976" (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Carved box with plaque, 1977 (Offsite-box 7)
    Plaque reads: "Presented to Ambassador A.D. Marshall [Brooke's son], the American Ambassador to Kenya by RADM W.J. Crowe Jr, USN, Commander, Middle East Force, 9 Feb 1977"
  - Invitation/Program from New York Foundling Hospital, 1978 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    Invitation and program to the dinner honoring Brooke Astor with the Elizabeth Seton Humanitarian Award.
  - Flag, 1983 (Folder FF-1)
    Inscribed on edge: "Houseflag of the Black Ball Line flown at the mainmast of 'Wavertree' on the occasion of the Brooklyn Bridge centennial celebration, May 24, 1983, East River, Pier 15, New York." Wavertree is the name of a ship at the South Street Seaport Museum. Textile. Measures approx 60"x36". (Stored in flat file drawer)
  - White House Christmas holiday print, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Brooke Astor funeral guest books (2), 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)